<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="im_exec">
  <title>Program (im_exec)</title>
  <para>
    This module will execute a program or script on startup and will read its standard
    output.
    It can be used to easily integrate with exotic log sources which can be read only with the
    help of scripts or programs.
  </para>

  <section id="im_exec_config">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      In addition to the <link linkend="config_module_common">common module directives</link>,
      the following can be used to configure the im_exec module instance.
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_exec_config_command"/>Command</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This directive is mandatory. It specifies the name of the script/program
	      to be executed.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_exec_config_arg"/>Arg</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      This is an optional parameter, multiple can be specified for each
	      argument needed to pass to the 
	      <link linkend="im_exec_config_command">Command</link>.
	      Note that specifying multiple arguments with one Arg directive separated with
	      spaces will not work because the Command will receive it as one argument,
	      so you will need to split them up.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_exec_config_inputtype"/>InputType</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      See the description about <link linkend="config_inputtype">InputType</link>
	      in the global module config section.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><anchor id="im_exec_config_restart"/>Restart</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <simpara>
	      Restart the process if it exits. There is a 1 second delay before it is restarted
	      in order not to DOS the system when a process is not behaving nicely.
	      Looping should be implemented in the script itself, this directive is only to
	      provide some safety against malfunctioning scripts and programs.
	      This boolean directive defaults to FALSE.
	    </simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="im_exec_config_examples">
    <title>Configuration examples</title>
    <para>
      <example>
	<title>Emulating im_file</title>
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../../config-examples/config-example-im_exec.xml" />
      </example>
      This exact same configuration is not recommended for real use because
      <link linkend="im_file">im_file</link> was designed to read log messages from files.
      This example only demonstrates the use of the im_exec module.
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
