<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="im_internal">
  <title>Internal (im_internal)</title>
  <para>
    This module makes it possible to insert internal log messages of nxlog into a route.
    nxlog generates messages about error conditions, debugging messages, etc. In addition
    internal messages can be also generated from the nxlog language using the
    <link linkend="core_proc_log_info">log_info()</link>,
    <link linkend="core_proc_log_warning">log_warning()</link> and
    <link linkend="core_proc_log_error">log_error()</link> procedure calls.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      Only messages with loglevel INFO and above are supported. Debug messages are ignored
      due to technical reasons. 
      For debugging purposes the direct logging facility should be used, see the global
      <link linkend="config_global_logfile">LogFile</link> and 
      <link linkend="config_global_loglevel">LogLevel</link> directives.
    </para>
    <para>
      One must be careful about the use of the im_internal module because it is easy to
      cause a message loop.
      For example consider the situation when the internal messages are sent to a database.
      If the database is experiencing errors which result in internal error messages then
      these are again routed to the database and this will trigger further error messages and
      is easy to see that this will result in a loop.
      In order to avoid a resource exhaustion, the im_internal module will drop its
      messages when the queue of next module in the route is full.
      It is recommended to always put the im_internal module instance in a separate route.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    The im_internal does not have any module specific configuration directives in addition
    to the <link linkend="config_module_common">common module directives</link>.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      If you require internal messages in syslog format, you need to explicitely convert them
      with <link linkend="pm_transformer">pm_transformer</link> or using the
      <link linkend="xm_syslog_proc_to_syslog_bsd">to_syslog_bsd()</link> procedure of
      the <link linkend="xm_syslog">xm_syslog</link> module, because the 
      <link linkend="im_mark_field_raw_event">$raw_event</link> field is not generated in
      syslog format.
    </para>
  </note>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../fields-im_internal.xml" />

  <section id="im_internal_config_examples">
    <title>Configuration examples</title>
    <para>
      <example>
	<title>Forwaring internal messages over syslog udp</title>
	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../../config-examples/config-example-im_internal.xml" />
      </example>
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
