<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="tips">
  <title>Tips and tricks</title>
   <para>
     This chapter addresses some common problems or log management requirements.
   </para>
   <section id="tips_no_logs">
     <title>Detecting a dead agent or log source</title>
     <para>
       It is a common requirement to be able to detect conditions when there are no log
       messages coming from a source. This usually indicates a problem with the log source,
       such as a broken network connection, server down or an application/system service
       is stuck.
       Usually this problem should be detected by monitoring tools (nagios, openview etc),
       but the absence of logs can be also a good reason to investigate such a situation.
     </para>

     <note>
       <para>
	 The <link linkend="im_mark">im_mark</link> module exists for a similar purpose.
	 It can emit messages periodically in order to show that the system logger
	 is not suffering problems.
       </para>
     </note>

     <para>
       The solution to this problem is the combined use of 
       <link linkend="lang_stat">statistical counters</link> and
       <link linkend="config_module_schedule">Scheduled</link> checks.
       The input module can update a statistical counter configured to calculate
       events per hour for example. In the same input module a 
       <link linkend="config_module_schedule">Schedule</link> block is defined
       which checks the value of the statistical counter periodically. 
       When the event rate is zero or drops below a certain limit, an appropriate 
       action can be <link linkend="config_module_schedule_exec">executed</link> such
       as sending out an alert email or generating an internal warning message.
       Note that probably there are other ways to solve this issue and this method
       might not be the optimal for all situations.
     </para>
     <example>
       <title>Alerting on absence of log messages</title>
       <para>
	 The following configuration example creates a statistical counter in the context of
	 the im_tcp module to calculate the number of events received per hour.
	 The <link linkend="config_module_schedule">Schedule</link> block within the
	 context of the same module checks the value of the "msgrate" statistical counter
	 and generates an internal error message when there were no logs received in the
	 past hour.
       </para>
       <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../config-examples/config-example-detect_no_logs.xml"/>
     </example>
   </section>

</chapter>
